Google Zürich Brandschenkestrasse 110 8002 Zürich Switzerland Phone: +41 78 9489 347 Address: Feldblumenstrasse 100, 8134 Adliswil E-mail: aleksandar.prokopec@gmail.com Website: http://axel22.github.io

ALEKSANDAR PROKOPEC

Personal Information

Birth date: 6. August 1985.

Slovenian, married

Swiss Permit B (2014 - 2019)

Summary

I am a computer science researcher with 7 years of academic and industrial experience. I published 12 peer-reviewed research publications, and led multiple software projects, supervised EPFL-hosted open source projects with external funding from Google, and organized a highly successful Coursera massive open online course on reactive programming. I have participated in several international collaborations with top universities and industrial partners. I participated on 17 industrial and research conferences and meetups, held 6 invited talks, and authored a textbook on concurrent programming in Scala. Since 2014, I am employed as a software engineer at Google.

Education

École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne, Lausanne, Switzerland

2009 - 2014

Ph.D. in Computer Science Advisor: Martin Odersky

Committee: Douglas Lea, Erik Meijer, Viktor Kuncak, Ola Svensson

Faculty of Electrical Engineering and Computing, Zagreb, Croatia

2004 - 2009

M.A. in Computer Science Advisor: Marin Golub

Professional Experience

Software Engineer, Google Inc., Zürich, Switzerland

2014 - 2016

Product area: Geo

- Maintaining a distributed logging infrastructure for Google Maps products.
- Working on a massively distributed system used to analyze Geo product usage.
- Led the implementation of a real-time distributed pipeline for spam detection. Awarded a Google Spot Bonus for this effort.
- Designed and implemented a test automation suite for product documentation.
- Main organizer of the team-internal monthly Hackathon events.
 Awarded a Google Peer Bonus for this effort.

Scala Open Source Developer, Scala Team, Lausanne, Switzerland

2009 - 2016

- Designed and implemented Scala Coroutines language extension for first-class coroutines, used to facilitate asynchronous programming.
- Designed and implemented Parallel Collections support for data-parallel programming (part of the Scala programming language since 2011).
- Core part of the Futures and Promises working group, aimed to design the support for asynchronous programming (part of Scala programming language since 2012).

- Maintained and improved the Scala compiler and the Scala standard library.
- Engaged in various open-source activities: ScalaDays conference organization, Scala Workshop program committee member, Scala Improvement Proposal process, online education (MOOCs) and documentation, etc.

Collaborations

FORTH Institute of Computer Science (Greece), 2015 – now Computer Architecture and VLSI Systems Laboratory
Research collaboration aimed at developing a novel high-performance concurrent data structures for traditional embedded systems.

Typesafe (USA), 2011 – now Collaborating on maintenance, development, technology and innovation exchange related to the Scala project (~30 Scala developers).

Akka team (Sweden), 2011 – 2012 Member of the working group (~10 people) that developed a unifying asynchronous programming framework for Scala.

Stanford University (USA), 2011 – 2013
Pervasive Parallelism Laboratory
Collaborated on the LMS and Delite compiler frameworks and runtimes for parallel embedded domain-specific languages (~10 people). Designed high-performance data structures and collections frontends.

Teaching Experience

External Lecturer, Co-Organizer, Reactive Programming and Parallelism
Co-organized, prepared materials and exercises, led teaching staff (~7 people)
on the undergraduate course on parallel, distributed, and asynchronous
programming at EPFL, ~90 students.

Lecturer, Co-Organizer, Parallel Programming and Data Analysis

2015

Coursera MOOC on parallel and asynchronous programming.

Lead Organizer, Principles of Reactive Programming Coursera MOOC on reactive programming in Scala, with 2 iterations and >60,000 participants so far.

- Coordinated a team of three lecturers during recording and lecture material production.
- Led graduate student teaching staff (~8 people), directed content production, designed and implemented exercise materials, managed the production of lecture videos, organized community TAs on Coursera.
- Received the EPFL IC Teaching Award for this effort.

Teaching Assistant, Functional Programming in Scala Required EPFL undergraduate course on functional programming (~160 students).

2010-2013

Research Interests

My focus is design and implementation of frameworks, programming languages, and runtime support for concurrent, parallel and distributed software development. I proposed and implemented novel persistent, concurrent and incremental data structures that support these programming paradigms. I use the Scala programming language as both the underlying development platform and research vehicle.

Thesis

Data Structures and Algorithms for Data-Parallel Computing EPFL 2014 in a Managed Runtime

Aleksandar Prokopec

Books

Learning Concurrent Programming in Scala

Packt Publishing 2014

Aleksandar Prokopec

Publications

Authored 12 international research publications and several technical reports.

Isolates, Channels and Event Streams for Composable Onward! 2015

Distributed Programming

Aleksandar Prokopec, Martin Odersky

Onward! 2015

Conc-Trees for Functional and Parallel Programming LCPC 2015

Aleksandar Prokopec, Martin Odersky

Languages and Compilers for Parallel Computing 2015

SnapQueue: Lock-Free Queue with Constant Time Snapshots **SCALA 2015**

Aleksandar Prokopec

Scala Symposium 2015, co-located with PLDI

Efficient Lock-Free Work-stealing Iterators for Data-Parallel Collections PDP 2015

Aleksandar Prokopec, Dmitry Petrashko, Martin Odersky Parallel, Distributed and Network-Based Processing 2015

Containers and Aggregates, Mutators and Isolates for Reactive Programming

SCALA 2014

Aleksandar Prokopec, Philipp Haller, Martin Odersky

Annual Scala Workshop 2014, co-located with ECOOP

LCPC 2013 Near Optimal Work-Stealing Tree Scheduler for Highly Irregular Data-Parallel Workloads

Aleksandar Prokopec, Martin Odersky

Languages and Compilers for Parallel Computing 2013

Composition and Reuse with Compiled Domain-Specific Languages ECOOP 2013

Arvind K. Sujeeth, Tiark Rompf, Kevin J. Brown,

HyoukJoong Lee, Hassan Chafi, Victoria Popic, Michael Wu,

Aleksandar Prokopec, Vojin Jovanovic, Martin Odersky, Kunle Olukotun

European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming 2013

LCPC 2012 FlowPools: A Lock-Free Deterministic Concurrent **Dataflow Abstraction** Aleksandar Prokopec, Heather Miller, Tobias Schlatter Philipp Haller, Martin Odersky Languages and Compilers for Parallel Computing 2012 Concurrent Tries with Efficient Non-blocking Snapshots PPOPP 2012 Aleksandar Prokopec, Nathan Bronson, Phil Bagwell, Martin Odersky Symposium on Principles and Practice of Parallel Programming 2012 Lock-Free Resizeable Concurrent Tries LCPC 2011 Aleksandar Prokopec, Phil Bagwell, Martin Odersky Languages and Compilers for Parallel Computing 2011 A Generic Parallel Collection Framework Euro-Par 2011 Aleksandar Prokopec, Phil Bagwell, Tiark Rompf, Martin Odersky Euro-Par 2011 Adaptive Mutation Operator Cycling ICADIWT 2009 Aleksandar Prokopec, Marin Golub International Conference on the Applications of Digital Information and Web Technologies 2009 Achieving Efficient Work-Stealing for Data-Parallel Collections April 2013 Aleksandar Prokopec, Martin Odersky Multi-Lane FlowPools: A Detailed Look September 2012 Tobias Schlatter, Aleksandar Prokopec, Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Martin Odersky FlowPools: A Lock-Free Deterministic Concurrent Dataflow June 2012 Abstraction – Proofs Aleksandar Prokopec, Heather Miller, Philipp Haller Cache-Aware Lock-Free Concurrent Hash Tries June 2011 Aleksandar Prokopec, Phil Bagwell, Martin Odersky Scala Programming Language, Scala team member 2009 - now • Scala Coroutines, lead Scala language extension for first-class coroutines, used for easier asynchronous programming. • Reactors Framework for Distributed Programming, lead

Programming framework aimed at building asynchronous,

• Scala-Blitz – High-Performance Data-Parallelism Framework, lead Scala module for highly efficient data-parallel programming.

composable, distributed systems.

Selected

Tech Reports

Open Source

- ScalaMeter Benchmarking Framework, lead
 Microbenchmarking and performance regression testing framework
 for Scala and JVM, adopted in various open source projects.
- Scala Futures & Promises (Scala Improvement Proposal 14), team member Asynchronous programming framework for Scala, used as a basic building block for other concurrency frameworks within the Scala ecosystem (part of standard Scala distribution since 2012).
- Parallel Collections Framework, lead Scala standard library module for data-parallel programming (part of the standard Scala distribution in 2011).

Java Group at Faculty of Electrical Engineering and Computing, Zagreb, 2006 – 2008

VHDLLab, team member
 Award-winning online educational VHDL editor for modeling and
 simulation of digital circuits (used as part of the computer
 science curriculum at the Faculty of Electrical Engineering
 and Computing in Zagreb since 2007).

Honors and Awards

Google Spot Bonus for the Distributed Real-Time Spam Detection Project	2015
Google Peer Bonus for the Team Hackathon Initiative	2015
Nominated for the Patrick Denantes Doctoral Thesis Award	2014
EPFL Outstanding Teaching Assistant Award	2013
LCPC Best Paper Presentation Award	2011
EPFL Computer Science Fellowship	2009 – 2010
University of Zagreb Rector Award for Best Project (VHDLLab)	2008
Faculty of Electrical Engineering and Computing Josip Loncar Award	2007
Faculty of Electrical Engineering and Computing Josip Loncar Award	2006
Participation in the International Physics Olympiad (IPhO)	2004
1st Place in the Croatian National Physics Competition (Finals)	2004
Participation in the Croatian National Physics Competition (Finals)	2002
Participation in the Croatian National Physics Competition (Finals)	2001

Selected Talks

Gave 20 academic and industrial talks, 6 as an invited speaker.

Gave 20 academic and industrial talks, 6 as an invited speaker.	
Isolates, Channels and Event Streams for Composable Distributed Programming Academic Conference Talk Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA, October 29, 2015	Onward! 2015
Scala – The Learning Curve Developer Conference Talk	Jazoon 2015
Zurich, Switzerland, October 23, 2015	
Conc-Tree Data Structure for Functional and Parallel Programming Academic Conference Talk	LCPC 2015
Raleigh, North Carolina, USA, September 10, 2015	

SnapQueue: Lock-Free Queue with Constant Time Snapshots

SCALA 2015

Academic Conference Talk

Portland, Oregon, USA, June 13, 2015

ScalaMeter - Performance Regression Testing Framework

Oracle VM Meetup 2014

Academic Meetup Talk

ETH, Zürich, Switzerland, September 11, 2014

Containers and Aggregates, Mutators and Isolates

SCALA 2014

for Reactive Programming Academic Conference Talk Uppsala, Sweden, July 28, 2014

Reactive Collections and 3D Engine Design

ScalaDays 2014

Industrial Conference Talk (800 attendees)

Berlin, Germany, June 24, 2014

Macro-based Scala Parallel Collections

Scala eXchange 2013

Industrial Conference Talk (350 attendees, invited talk)

London, UK, December 2, 2013

Work-Stealing Tree Scheduling

LCPC 2013

Academic Conference Talk

San Jose, CA, USA, September 26, 2013

Scala as a Research Tool

ECOOP 2013

ECOOP Tutorial (w/ Heather Miller and Philipp Haller)

Montpellier, France, July 1, 2013

Scala Performance Regression Testing

Scala eXchange 2012

Industrial Conference Talk (invited talk) London, UK, November 19, 2012

Parallel Concurrent Hash Tries

ScalaDays 2012

Industrial Conference Talk (400 attendees)

London, UK, April 18, 2012

Concurrent Hash Tries in Scala

Croatian IEEE Chapter Meetup

Academic Meetup Talk (invited talk)

Zagreb, Croatia, April 11, 2012

Concurrent Tries with Efficient Non-Blocking Snapshots

PPOPP 2012

Academic Conference Talk

New Orleans, Louisiana, USA, February 29, 2012

Lock-Free Resizeable Concurrent Tries

LCPC 2011

Academic Conference Talk

Fort Collins, CO, USA, September 9, 2011

Generic Parallel Collection Framework

Euro-Par 2011

Academic Conference Talk

Bordeaux, France, September 2, 2011

Parallel Collections Scala eXchange 2011

Industrial Conference Talk (280 attendees, invited talk)

London, UK, June 15, 2011

Scala Parallel Collections ScalaDays 2011

Industrial Conference Talk Palo Alto, CA, USA, June 3, 2011

Introduction to Scala JUG Meetup 2011

Industrial Talk, Java User Group Grenoble (invited talk)

Grenoble, France, March, 2011

Parallel Collections ScalaDays 2010

Industrial Conference Talk (150 attendees, invited talk)

Lausanne, Switzerland, April 15, 2010

External Service

Reviewer or program committee member of 7 scientific conferences and journals.

High-Level Parallel Programming and Applications, program committee member 2016		
Transactions on Computers 2015, journal submission reviewer	2015	
Scala Workshop 2014, program committee member	7/2014	
High-Level Parallel Programming and Applications 2014, external reviewer	4/2014	
ECOOP 2013, external reviewer	7/2013	
Scala Workshop 2013, program committee member (co-chair)	7/2013	
ScalaDays 2010, external reviewer	6/2010	
ICADIWT 2009, external reviewer	8/2009	

Supervised Projects¹

M.Sc. level

Supervised 14 bachelor and master student projects.

Joël Rossier, MacroGL Scala.JS Backend B.Sc. level	2/2014 – 6/2014
Sven Reber, MacroGL API Extensions B.Sc. level	2/2014 - 6/2014
Gwangbae Choi, ScalaMeter Inline Benchmarking B.Sc. level	2/2014 – 6/2014
Kristof Szabo, ScalaMeter Java API B.Sc. level	2/2014 – 6/2014
Nicolas Stucki, Scala Multiset Collection	9/2013 - 1/2014

¹EPFL research labs prepare projects for B.Sc./M.Sc. students to complete for credits. These projects are designed and supervised by EPFL doctoral assistants.

Timo Babst, Data-Parallel Raytracer B.Sc. level	9/2013 - 1/2014
Clément Moutet, Data-Parallel Flocking Algorithm B.Sc. level	9/2013 - 1/2014
Roman Zoller, ScalaMeter D3js Frontend M.Sc. level	2/2013 - 6/2013
Tobias Schlatter, FlowSeqs: Barrier-Free ParSeqs M.Sc. level, co-supervision w/ Philipp Haller & Heather Miller	9/2012 - 1/2013
Roger Vion, Improvements to ScalaMeter B.Sc. level	9/2012 - 1/2013
Tobias Schlatter, Multi-Lane FlowPools M.Sc. level, co-supervision w/ Philipp Haller & Heather Miller	2/2012 - 6/2012
Bruno Studer, A Non-Blocking Concurrent Queue Algorithm B.Sc. level	2/2012 - 6/2012
Ngoc Duy Pham, Scala Benchmarking Suite – Performance Regression Pinpointing M.Sc. level	8/2011 - 1/2012
Pamela Delgado, Scala Invariant Verifier M.Sc. level	8/2011 - 1/2012
Supervised 4 Google Summer of Code projects.	
Krzysztof Janosz, ScalaMeter Binary Compatible Serialization Format and Invocation Measurers	5/2015 - 9/2015
Dmitry Petrashko, Specializing Parallel Collections with Scala Macros	5/2013 - 9/2013
Ivan Oreskovic, Porting Scala Parallel Collections to the Android Platform	5/2012 - 9/2012
Heather Miller, Parallel Collections Extensions	5/2011 - 9/2011

GSoC Projects²

²The Scala Team is a regular host of Google Summer of Code Projects. These are 3-month paid projects offered to students all over the world, sponsored by Google and supervised by members of various open-source organizations.

References

Martin Odersky

Faculty of Computer, Communication, and Information Science École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne

**** +41 21 693 68 63

⊠ martin.odersky@epfl.ch

Philipp Haller

School of Computer Science and Communication

KTH Royal Institute of Technology

C +41 76 205 39 32

⊠ phaller@kth.se